[Music]
the story of life on Earth is a story of
starvation ash from massive volcanoes
and asteroids block out the sun killing
the plants which then killed most
everything else as Darwin pointed out
though from this war of nature from
famine and death the most exalted object
that we are capable of conce leing aose
namely us we are particularly well
adapted to prolonged fasting evolving in
a contact of scarcity is believed to
have shaped our exceptional ability to
store large amounts of calories when
food is available of course now our
ability to easily pack on the pounds is
leading to Modern diseases like obesity
and type 2 diabetes but without the
ability to store so much body fat we may
not have made it to tell the tale and
it's not just asteroids millions of
years ago all of Upper Egypt was dying
of hunger read an inscription on an
Egyptian tomb from about 4,000 years ago
uh to such degree that everyone had come
to eating his children or just hundreds
of years ago parents killed their
children and children killed their
parents and ate them the bodies of
executed criminals were eagerly snatched
from The Gallows wiping out as many as
2third of the population of Italy
onethird of the population of Paris so
we don't have to go back to ancient
history even the most secure and
affluent populations of today need only
Trace their history back a short
distance for example nearly 200 famines
in Britain over the last 2,000
years now uh we tend to be suffering
from too much food which carries its own
problems but might there be any negative
consequences to not ever starving this
was a question raised 50 years ago I
mean if our physiology is so well tuned
to periodic starvation Maybe by
eliminating that we may be doing harm to
our overall
well-being we just didn't know the lack
of research in the area of starvation
was attributed to the difficulty of
securing willing human subjects so what
little we had came from unwilling
subjects Physicians with the Warsaw
Ghetto made detailed accounts before
they themselves succumbed or Irish
Republican prisoners starving themselves
to death after up to 73 days on Hunger
Strike but starvation isn't necessarily
the same as fasting an issue raised in
medical journals over a century ago
starvation is normally a forced mentally
stressful and chronic condition whereas
therapeutic fasting is voluntary limited
duration and usually practiced by people
who you know start out with adequate
nutrition therapeutic fasting where' we
get this idea of fasting therapy fasting
for medical purposes well it may have
originally rose out of the observation
that when people get acutely ill they
tend to lose their appetite so maybe
there's something in the body's wisdom
to stopping eating that's presumably
where the whole you know star of a fever
Fork lore came from uh there was the
sense that fasting forward's physiologic
rest for the body not just the digestive
tract but throughout allowing the body
to concentrate on healing it was
evidently an Open Secret that
veterinarians used to hospital dogs only
to fast them back to health and so maybe
the theory went it might work for people
too Beyond just freeing up all the
resources that would normally be used
for nutrient digestion and storage
there's this concept that during fasting
our cells switch over to some sort of
protection mode why would fasting reduce
free radical damage and inflammation and
bolster cellular protection it's the
that which doesn't kill us makes a
stronger concept known as hormesis
so that's kind of the opposite of the
let the body rest Theory it's more like
Let the Body stress the stress of
fasting May steal the body against other
stresses coming your way this was
demonstrated perhaps most starkly in a
set of cringeworthy experiments in which
mice were blasted with hirosima level
gamma radiation sufficient to kill 50%
within 2 weeks but of the mice would
first been intermittently faster for for
6 weeks before not a single one died
it's this kind of dramatic data that led
to you know extraordinary claims like
therapeutic fasting could drive half of
all doctors out of business but you
don't know until you put it to the test
which we'll explore
[Music]
next for